<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<section
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  lang="en"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="additional_features">

  <title>Additional features</title>
  <section xml:id="menu">
    <title>The 
      <guimenu>Action</guimenu>menu</title>
    <para>From the 
      <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>menu you can access your 
      <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>and configure 
      <guimenuitem>Servers</guimenuitem>. If your enthusiasm for GêBR has lead you to read the
      whole manual, you have probably used almost all available features found in these options.
      But just in case, below you will find the documentation for these options.</para>
    <section>
      <title>Preferences</title>
      <para>The details you provide in the 
        <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>dialog box will be adopted as the default by GêBR.
        Specifically:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>User name:</guilabel>will be used as the default for 
            <guilabel>Author:</guilabel>when you create Projects, Lines and Flows.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>Email:</guilabel>will be used as the default for 
            <guilabel>Email:</guilabel>when you create Projects, Lines and Flows.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <guilabel>User's menus directory:</guilabel>will be the default directory where 
            <emphasis>GêBR's Menus</emphasis>are maintained ( 
            <filename class="extension">mnu</filename>files).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <figure>
        <mediaobject>
          <caption>Preferences menu opens a dialog box where you edit the user name, email,
            menu's directory and the HTML editor.</caption>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/GeBR_preferences.png" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>Advanced settings in Preferences menu expands the dialog box where you edit the
        maestro server and HTML editor.</para>
      <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Advanced Settings</emphasis>
      </para>
      <mediaobject>
        <caption>Advanced Settings of Preferences menu</caption>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/GeBR_preferences_advanced.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maestro Server: will be the default for Maestro Server when you start GêBR, the
            localhost is the default for Maestro Server when you connect GêBR for the first
            time.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>HTML editor: the default text editor that GêBR will open when creating reports on
            Projects, Lines and Flows.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="servers_configuration">
    <title>Servers configuration</title>
    <para>GêBR can take benefit of the resources of multiple machines. To handle it, GêBR is
      segmented in three layers:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>The host machine (GêBR-client), from where the user sends requests</listitem>
      <listitem>An intermediate layer (GêBR-maestro), where all the jobs are coordinated</listitem>
      <listitem>Executors (GêBR-daemons), where the jobs are executed</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <mediaobject>
      <caption>Layers of execution of GêBR</caption>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="../images/GeBR_servers_maestro_diagram.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>The user can be connected to one maestro at once. Each maestro, in turn, can be connected
      to many daemons. To ease the task of handling of files by the maestro, one requirement is that
      all the daemons must be in the same Network File System (NFS).</para>
    <para>The Servers Interface has three parts: 
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Maestro entry- central unit of coordination of multiple machines</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Servers configuration - choose the daemons associated to the current maestro</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Groups configuration- configure the groups of daemons on the current maestro</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist></para>
    <section>
      <title>Maestro Entry</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <caption>Maestro entry</caption>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/GeBR_servers_maestro_entry.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>In the upper part of the Servers Interface, there is an entry in which the user can put
        the desired machine to use as maestro. A requirement is that the package GêBR-maestro must be
        installed on that machine. The state of the connection between GêBR and the maestro is shown
        by the right-side icon: 
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>connected (<inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../../common-images/gtk-connect.png" />
                </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>)</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>disconnected (<inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../../common-images/gtk-disconnect.png" />
                </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>)</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>error (<inlinemediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                  <imagedata fileref="../../common-images/gtk-dialog-warning.png" />
                </imageobject>
          </inlinemediaobject>)</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Servers configuration</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <caption>Servers</caption>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/GeBR_servers_daemons.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>Once selected a coordinator machine (maestro), the user can associate machines to that
        maestro.</para>
      <para>The lines represent the machines associated to the maestro. Each line has two columns:
        the first column shows if the option Auto-connect is activated or not; the second column
        shows the name (hostname) of the machine. The user can add a new machine by clicking over New
        and entering the name of address of the machine.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Groups configuration</title>
      <para>The user can use just a couple of the machines associated to the maestro. Using
        different subsets of machines can be managed through the creation of groups of
        machines.</para>
      <para>In the bottom part of the Servers interface, the user can create/edit daemons groups.
        The functionality is through mouse Drag and Drop.</para>
      <mediaobject>
        <caption>Groups</caption>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/GeBR_servers_groups_new.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
      <para>To create a group, the user needs to click over a server in the list and drag it to the
        + icon. A text box is going to be prompted for the name of the group. Groups with same names
        are not accepted.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="execution_log">
    <title>The execution log</title>
    <para>GêBR remembers most of the users actions, as well as the results of these actions, in
      the so called 
      <emphasis>execution log</emphasis>. This log is shown at the bottom of the main window, which
      can be presented in the collapsed form (default) or the expanded form like the window
      below.</para>
    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <caption>At the bottom of GêBR's main window you will find the execution log, which
          displays information on all of GêBR processes.</caption>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/janela_log_execucao.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <tip>
      <para>In 
        <menuchoice>
          <guimenu>Actions</guimenu>
          <guimenuitem>Preferences</guimenuitem>
        </menuchoice>at the bottom of the dialog box, we can see the box 
        <guilabel>Load past-execution log</guilabel>. By checking this box we choose to exhibit the
        whole log, including actions from past dates. By leaving the box unchecked we choose to
        have a compact log, which only shows actions that have taken place since GêBR's last
        initialization.</para>
    </tip>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="import_samples">
    <title>Sample projects</title>
    <para>In the Help menu, besides the general Help section, we can import available
      samples:</para>
    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <caption>Screenshot of the Samples Menu</caption>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/samples_en.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</section>
