<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<section
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  lang="en"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="overview">
  
  <title>Concepts</title>

  <section xml:id="concepts_elements">
    <title>Projects, Lines and Flows</title>
    
    <para>The processing of a seismic data is carried out
      by <emphasis>processing flows</emphasis>. A processing flow is a
      chain of programs, which sequentially operates on an input data to
      produce an output data from it. For example, processing flows can be
      assembled to accomplish tasks like <emphasis>spike
	deconvolution</emphasis>, <emphasis>ground-roll
	atenuation</emphasis>, <emphasis>NMO correction</emphasis>, and so
      on.</para>

    <para>In GêBR, processing flows are referenced
      as <emphasis role="bold">Flows</emphasis>. The complete processing of
      a seismic data (also known as a <emphasis>seismic line</emphasis>,
      in 2D case) involves several processing flows. The set of processing
      flows is referenced as a <emphasis role="bold">Line</emphasis> in
      the GêBR interface. Furthermore, it is common to have many seismic
      lines acquired on a target area. A set of seismic lines is known as
      a <emphasis role="bold">Project</emphasis>, in GêBR.</para>

    <para>In summary, GêBR has three levels organization, from top to bottom:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Project</emphasis>: It is a set of
          <emphasis role="bold">Lines</emphasis>. A Project has only few
	  basic information and is used to cluster lines related
	  somehow.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Line</emphasis>: It is a set of 
          <emphasis role="bold">Flows</emphasis>. During the setup of
          the Line, some important choices have to be made, mainly
          concerning the organization of the <emphasis>processing
            products</emphasis> (intermediate data, figures, tables, etc)
          produced during the processing of a seismic line.
	</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
	<para>
	  <emphasis role="bold">Flow</emphasis>: It is a sequence of
	  programs, designed to accomplish a specific task, in the
	  course of the processing the seismic data.
	</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>
      Thus, before creating and executing Flows, it's necessary to create
      at least one Project owning one
      Line. <xref linkend="projects_lines_create_projects"/>,
      <xref linkend="projects_lines_create_lines"/> and
      <xref linkend="flows_browser_create_flow"/> explain how this is
      accomplished.
    </para>

    <para>To assemble a Flow, the user has not only to select the
      programs, but also configure them properly, through their
      parameters. Once the Flow is ready, it is time to actually execute
      it.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="concepts_connections">
    <title>GêBR players</title>

    <para>The GêBR set of tools is composed by three main player
      categories: <emphasis role="bold">GêBR</emphasis> (the interface
      itself), <emphasis role="bold">Maestros</emphasis>,
      and <emphasis role="bold">working machines</emphasis>. But who
      are those guys?</para>

    <para>The GêBR interface, sometimes refered as GêBR only, is the
      graphical interface with whom the user interacts with to build
      processing flows, execute them, inspect results, etc. Usually, this
      interface is installed and is running in the machine user has
      physical contatct with.</para>

    <para>Through GêBR, it is possible to take advantage of as many
      machines as the user has access, to run processing flows. Those
      machines are referenced as <emphasis role="bold">working
      machines</emphasis> (or sometimes,
      as <emphasis>servers</emphasis>). They may be local, meaning the
      user is physically using them, or remote, meaning the user has
      access to them through the network. No matter where the machines
      are, they are equally treated by GêBR, which means that the user
      does not have to care about that.</para>

    <para>However, GêBR does not talk directly with the working
      machines. This communication is established through another
      player, the <emphasis role="bold">Maestro</emphasis>. It acts as
      a coordinator of the working machines. Without interference,
      Maestro collects information about the state of each working
      machine and ranks them according to their capabilities and
      available resources at time. Therefore, Maestro can take smart
      decisions about which machines are best suited to run the
      job.</para>
  
    <para>The working machines put their computational power at
      disposal of the Maestro. Under Maestro's coordination the
      working machines can even cooperate to conclude processing jobs
      fasters.</para>
 
   <para>When the user decides to execute a flow, GêBR sends this
      request to the Maestro, giving rise to
      a <emphasis role="bold">job</emphasis>. However the Maestro does
      not execute the job itself. Indeed, it dispatches the job to
      some of the working machines, under its control. Besides,
      Maestro collects the results and all information about the job,
      sending them back to GêBR, where they are presented to the
      user.</para>

   <para>This communication process, despiste complex, is completely
     transparent to the user, which can concentrate on processing
     seismic data, leaving all technical details to GêBR.</para>
  </section>
    
  <section xml:id="concepts_gebr_gui_layout">
    <title>GêBR interface layout</title>

    <para>
      The GêBR interface is intentionally simple. It is organized in tabs:
      <itemizedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <guilabel>Projects and Lines</guilabel>: for creating and manipulating
	  Projects and Lines;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <guilabel>Flows</guilabel>: for creating and executing Flows;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <guilabel>Flow Editor</guilabel>: for editing and executing a Flow;
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <guilabel>Job Control</guilabel>: for inspecting the results.
	</listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <!--
      <figure>
	<mediaobject>
          <caption>GêBR tabs.</caption>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="../images/GeBR_tabs.png"/>
          </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>
      -->
    </para>
    
    <para>
      GêBR also has additional resources in menu bar, on the top of
      the window.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          Actions
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Preferences</guilabel>: User preferences;
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Connections Assistant</guilabel>: Step-by-step
              guided setup of the main connections performed by GêBR;
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Maestro/Servers</guilabel>: Configuration of
              Maestro, Servers and Groups of servers;
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Quit</guilabel>: quit GêBR.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          Help 
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Help</guilabel>: GêBR's documentation;
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>Examples</guilabel>: examples of seismic processing;
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <guilabel>About</guilabel>: GêBR's version, license and
              staff information.
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <!--
    <figure>
      <mediaobject>
        <caption>GêBR's menus bar</caption>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../images/GeBR_menubar.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    -->
    </section>
</section>  

