<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<chapter
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  lang="en"
  version="5.0"
  xml:id="what_is_gebr">

  <title>What is GêBR?</title>
  <para>GêBR is a simple graphical
    interface<indexterm><primary>GêBR</primary><secondary>the
    interface</secondary></indexterm> which <emphasis>facilitates
    geophysical data processing</emphasis>. GêBR is <emphasis>not a
    package for processing</emphasis>, it is designed
    to <emphasis>integrate</emphasis> a large variety of free
    processing packages, such as <emphasis>Seismic Un*x</emphasis>
    and <emphasis>Madagascar</emphasis>.</para>

  <para>GêBR can manage projects and lines, assemble and execute flows
    and follow the results of the data processing. Everything in a
    simple and friendly way.</para>

  <para>Being a <emphasis>free software</emphasis>, anyone can use and
    customize GêBR for free, according to the terms of the
    <emphasis>GNU Public License</emphasis>. That makes this software
    very attractive for academic research and for use in
    courses.</para>

  <section>
    <title>GêBR Project</title>

    <para>The <emphasis>GêBR
    Project</emphasis><indexterm><primary>GêBR
    Project</primary></indexterm> was initially proposed to develop
    and promote the GêBR interface. During 2007–2008, the core team of
    developers had offered several courses on seismic processing with
    GêBR, at the most active research centers in Geophysics in
    Brazil. Around 200 students and professionals had direct
    contact with the project on that period. In that process the GêBR
    observed a demand for integration efforts among Brazilian
    geophysical community. That motivated a redefinition for the
    project’s goals.</para>

    <blockquote><emphasis>The main objective of GêBR is to stimulate the
    integration of the Brazilian Geophysical Community by providing an
    interface to geophysical data processing that could be used not
    only for teaching purposes but also as a research dissemination
    vehicle.</emphasis></blockquote>

    <para>For more information, visit the project's official site:
			<emphasis><link xlink:href="http://www.gebrproject.com">
					http://www.gebrproject.com</link></emphasis>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
        <title>What's new</title>
    <itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				Version 0.20.0 <emphasis>(current)</emphasis>
					<para>This release of GêBR brings a lot of new exciting features to ease 
						the handling and the management of flows and programs, including:</para>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<emphasis>Joining of Flow Editor and Flow Browse tabs navigation:</emphasis> now 
						through Flows tab is possible control all the actions about flows and programs, 
						thus the activities at GêBR are much more centralized, fast and easy 
						(see <xref linkend="flows_tab"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<emphasis>Flows tab powered:</emphasis> the work on GêBR is wonderfully fast, because 
						now it's possible to see in the same tab a summary information of the flow, edit 
						programs and their parameters and also to see the output of the flow's execution. 
						(see <xref linkend="flows_tab"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<emphasis>New Toolbar:</emphasis> the new toolbar makes the GêBR interface much 
						more clean. Just the frequently used actions are on the toolbar, the other actions 
						are placed in More menu (see <xref linkend="project_line"/> and 
						see <xref linkend="flows_tab"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<emphasis>Quick access to Menus list:</emphasis> the new toolbar brings a new way 
						of to access the menu list. Through the menu list icon it's possible to see all 
						the menus and add them to the flows in few clicks 
						(see <xref linkend="flows_menus_list"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<emphasis>Execution modes:</emphasis> now there are two options of execution, it's 
						possible run the flows directly or choose and save the preferences of execution and 
						then run the flows. So, it's just necessary changing the preferences once or when 
						it's desired run a flow in a different way from the standard mode 
						(see <xref linkend="flows_execute_flow"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<emphasis>Snapshots:</emphasis> this feature gives much more freedom to the flows, 
						all the important status of flows can be saved and reverted anytime, thus 
						it's possible modify loosely the flows and their programs 
						(see <xref linkend="flows_snapshots"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<emphasis>Search on documentation:</emphasis> never more fell lost among the 
						documentation and reports. Starting this release of GêBR it's possible to 
						search terms in the reports of projects, lines and flows and also in the flow 
						summary (see <xref linkend="flows_tab"/>).
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Version 0.18.0 <emphasis>(May 24th 2012)</emphasis>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						Prior to this version, lines could have some directories,
						known as <emphasis>line's paths</emphasis>. Shortcuts to
						those directories were available in each file browse
						dialog. From this version, to each line it is associated a
						standard hierarchy of directories (see definition in
						<xref linkend="projects_lines_line_paths"/> and example of
						usage in <xref linkend="flows_edit_input_output"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						Now it's possible to change the line's maestro (see
						<xref linkend="projects_lines_change_the_maestro_of_a_line"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						GêBR correctly displays remote folder (see
						<xref linkend="technical_aspects_remote_browsing"/>).
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				Version 0.16.0<emphasis> (January 30th 2012)</emphasis>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>The concept of <emphasis>Maestro</emphasis> is born,
						allowing to execute
						jobs in multiples machines.  (see
						<xref linkend="additional_features_maestro_servers_configuration"
							/> and <xref linkend="technical_aspects_multicores"
							/>).</listitem>
					<listitem>Now it is possible to control the number of cores
						used by the jobs of GêBR and change the priority of
						execution of a job (see
						<xref linkend="technical_aspects_multicores" /> and
						<xref linkend="technical_aspects_priority_execution"
							/>).</listitem>
					<listitem>Renewed interface: new functionalities and
						improved usability.</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
			<para>
			</para>
			<listitem>
				Version 0.14.0 <emphasis>(October 3rd 2011):</emphasis>
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						The variables dictionary and the program parameters accept
						arithmetic expressions (see section
						<xref linkend="technical_aspects_dictionary_variables"/>).
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						Repetitive processes can be automatized by the use of
						loops (see section <xref linkend="flows_loop"/>).
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Technical Information</title>
    <para>This user guide is for GêBR <emphasis>version
      0.20.0</emphasis>. The images used in this guide were captured
      in a <emphasis>Ubuntu 10.04</emphasis> based system. Therefore, slight 
      differences may be observed in case another
      operating system is being used. For specific installation instructions for
      each operating system, see the
      <emphasis><link xlink:href="http://www.gebrproject.com/install-guide">install
      guide</link></emphasis>, in the
      <emphasis><link xlink:href="http://www.gebrproject.com">project's
      official site</link></emphasis>.</para>
  </section>
  <!-- Time da GêBR (GêBR Team) -->
  <xi:include href="gebr-team.xml" />
  
</chapter>
